<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Breach of covenant, a ruinating sinne. as it was preached at Clare in Suff. Novemb. 3. And now published for the good of adjoyning parts, especially those of Hinkford Hundred in Essex. / By a Country Minister.</title>
            <author>Country minister.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4335A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173245</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578179</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45578179</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172134</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77297)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172134)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2615:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Breach of covenant, a ruinating sinne. as it was preached at Clare in Suff. Novemb. 3. And now published for the good of adjoyning parts, especially those of Hinkford Hundred in Essex. / By a Country Minister.</title>
                  <author>Country minister.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Paine, for Edward Blackmore, in Pauls Church Yard, at the signe of the Angell.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Imprimatur Edmond Calamy."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Hosea X, 4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Covenants --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Judgement of God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172134:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Breach of Covenant, A RVINATING SINNE. As it was preached at Clare in Suff. Novemb. 3. And now publiſhed for the good of adjoyning parts, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe of Hinkford Hundred in Eſſex. By a Country Miniſter.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng" subtype="imprimatur">
               <body>
                  <p>Imprimatur</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Edmond Calamy,</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>London Printed by Tho. Paine, for Edward Blackmore. in Pauls Church Yard, at the ſigne of the Angell. 1648.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Decorative title page border.</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:172134:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172134:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>BREACH OF COVENANT, A Ruinating Sinne.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Hoſea 10. chap. 4. ver. 7</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>They have ſpoken words, ſwearing falſly in making a Covenant: Thus Judgment ſpringeth up as Hemlock in the furrows of the feild.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord diſcovering his purpoſe to ſmite the people of Iſrael, and to ruinate them, doth, for the clearing of his juſtice, by the Prophet diſcover their ſinnes, which provoak't him to do this thing: this, through the whole former part of this prophecy.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of this chapter, the Prophet from the Lord gives in charge againſt them divers ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Ingratitude towards God, manifeſted in their ſelf-ſeeking, and ſelf-confidence, ver. 1. <hi>Iſrael is an empty vine, he bringeth forth fruit to himſelf.</hi> The people are nothing for God, nothing for goodneſſe, Gods worſhip, his waies and will, they are all for themſelves, their own fancies, vanities, &amp;c. or elſe, Though the Lord goe about to ſtrip this people bare, yet they think by their Idolatries to ſecure themſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Diviſion, heart-diviſion. ver. 2. <hi>Their heart is divided,</hi> divided from God, from goodneſſe, yea amongſt themſelves one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through pride, peeviſhneſſe, envie, malice, coveteouſneſſe, one for this way, another for that way, &amp;c. <hi>One heart with God, for God, in God is a great bleſſing,</hi> and that which God imparts only in a day of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172134:3"/> love; but a divided heart, a double heart is a great curſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Abuſe of pollicy, of Magiſtracy, of lawfull government, verſe 3. <hi>(For now they ſhall ſay) we have no King, &amp;c.</hi> This they did two wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In an overvaluing way, looking too much to their King, truſting in him, and ſetting him up in the room of God. Oh a King ſhall ſave, a King ſhall help, &amp;c. thus as the words are here tranſlated, God will break this their ſtaffe, and bring down their high lookes in this regard; <hi>Now they ſhall ſay we have no King, &amp;c.</hi> the time haſtens wherein the Lord will overthrow their government, take their King away, make them ſlaves to ſtrangers, and then they ſhall be forced to confeſſe, that becauſe they feared not the Lord, their King could doe nothing for them to ſecure them, to ſettle them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in an undervaluing way ſlighting government, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning it, ſetting light by their Kings; thus, as the words are tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated in the preſent tenſe. <hi>For now they ſay, we have no King: for wee feare not God, what then hath a King to doe with us?</hi> Having caſt off the feare of God, they did caſt off all feare of Government; they would not have their Kings command them, they would command their Kings; they claimed a lawleſſe liberty every man reſolving to do what he pleaſes, and would no further regard their Governours nor their laws then as they ſuited with their luſts. This is evident in the hiſtory of thoſe times.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth ſinne given in charge againſt them is mentioned in the text; wherein we have two parts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the ſinne it ſelf, plainly expreſſed, this is perjury, breach of Covenant. <hi>They have ſpoken words, ſwearing falſly in making a Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the fruit of this ſinne wrapped up under Metaphors. <hi>Thus iudgement ſpringeth up as hemlock in the furrows of the field.</hi> This fruit is two fold according to the divers interpretation of this latter part of the verſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt it brought down judgement from God, awakened wrath in him, and cauſed him to ſet himſelf againſt them, and to follow them with his plagues; it cauſed God to bring downe judgement upon them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Certain and ſudden judgement. <hi>Thus iudgement ſprings up,</hi> Gods judgements come in upon them when they think not of them, they increaſe inſenſibly, Gods hand is out againſt them day and night, their judgment ſlumbers not, ſlacks not.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:172134:3"/>
            <p n="2">2. Banefull, and bitter judgement. Iudgement ſprings up as <hi>Hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock,</hi> a banefull weed; as <hi>Wormewood,</hi> a bitter herbe: Gods hand, that is out againſt them, and his judgements that are upon them, poyſon their comforts, imbitter their ſweets, cauſe them to waſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, bring them to deaths doore.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Generall judgement; Iudgement ſprings up in the <hi>furrows of the field,</hi> in all parts, in all places; Gods hand out againſt them in the City, and Gods hand out againſt them in the Country, the wrath of God followes them in every place, and ſpreads over the whole land, though the people are inſenſible of it. This is one fruit of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, and Breach of Covenant.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It corrupted judgement among men (for this alſo is the <hi>Iudgement</hi> here meant) it overthrew Iuſtice, and righteouſneſſe, and faithfull dealing, and bred injuſtice, cruelty, oppreſſion, and this <hi>in all the furrowes;</hi> in all parts of the Land, in all Courts of Iuſtice, in all places of Iudgement; the poore oppreſſed people ſought for help, and men in place ſeemed to hold forth an helping hand; but the remedy was worſe than the diſeaſe, the Iuſtice adminiſtred was banefull, the Iudgement pronounced was bitter. Theſe were the fruits of Iſrael's breach of Covenant; the face of Heaven was clouded upon them, Gods wrath abode on them there was nothing but confuſion and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order in the State, till the Aſſyrian, Gods ſcourge, came and ſwept them wholly away. All this is evident in the hiſtory of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Jſrael</hi> in it's old age; me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g times, the times that immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did praecede the removall of this people out of the Land of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. Thus have you the ſtate of theſe words; the matter of them being a diſcovery of thoſe Iudgements that did haſten <hi>Jſraels</hi> ruine, and a principall ſinne that did cauſe thoſe Iudgements. I have at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent but one leſſen to hold forth from them, namly this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct</hi> Breach of Covenant, ſwearing falſly in making a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, is a very ruinating ſinne.</p>
            <p>Jn the handling of this J ſhall ſhew you. 1. What breach of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant brings ruine. 2. How breach of Covenant brings ruine up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a people, or a perſon, that are guilty of it. 3. Why this is a ruinating ſinne. The two former ſerve for explication, The latter for confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the point.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What breach of Covenant brings ruine; That ye may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtand this, know there is a twofold Covenant, a twofold
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172134:4"/> Oath made and ſworn by men, in a promiſſory way.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Jllicitum, impium,</hi> an unlawfull Covenant, a wicked and helliſh Oath,<note place="margin">Not of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull Oath.</note> when men covenant and ſweare to doe that which is in it ſelf utterly unlawfull, oppoſing directly Gods glory, humane ſociety, our own or our Neighbours good.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.22. ver. 32.3.</note> Such was <hi>Davids Oath,</hi> which he made in his paſſion, <hi>of cutting off all that belonged to Nabal's familie:</hi> The good man when he comes to himſelfe, bleſſed God for his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting grace in ſending <hi>Abigail</hi> to be an inſtrument of hindring him from acting ſuch horrid crueltie.<note place="margin">Mar. 6.22, 23.</note> Such was <hi>Herods Oath</hi> in ſwearing to doe any thing (though never ſo unjuſt) for the dancing Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zell. Such was the vow of thoſe Aſſaſſinats that out of blind zeale, covenanted to murther <hi>Paul.</hi> Or when men covenant to neglect to doe that which the Law of God and of Nature calls for:<note place="margin">Acts 23.12.13.</note> Such was that <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ow</hi> which the <hi>Seribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes</hi> taught their Diſciples to make <hi>conſcience</hi> of, therein making <hi>void Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and maitaining their own traditions,</hi> mentioned by our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.5, 6. The breach of ſuch a Covenant, ſuch an Oath as this, is not ruinating; yea the keeping of it haſtens ruine, while men herein add wickednes to wickednes. Such covenants, ſuch oathes are to be repented of, are not to be performed.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">But of a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Oath,</note>2. <hi>Licitum, pium,</hi> A lawfull Covenant, an honeſt, a lawfull oath, when men ſolemnly engage themſelves either to God, or man for the performing of ſuch things as are agreeable to the revealed will of God, conduce to the advancement of Gods glory, the furtherance of humane ſociety, and our own or our Neighbours good; or for the avoiding, and laying aſide of ſuch things as fight againſt any of theſe. This is binding whether it be abſolute or conditionall, whether it be voluntary, or coacted, and the breach of ſuch a Covenant, the falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of ſuch an oath, is the ſinne that the Prophet gives in charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this people of <hi>Jſraell</hi> in this place.<note place="margin">Men guilty of breach of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enant.</note> This is that ſinne that brings ruine upon all thoſe that abide under the guilt of it. Now the guilt of this ſinne is contracted.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">VVhen they Covenant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſhly</note>Firſt, when men covenant raſhly, ſweare unadviſedly, engaging themſelves ſolemnly, for the doing of that, and the avoiding of that which they are wholly ignorant of, and have no wayes in their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; when men make covenanting and ſwearing a matter of forme, a thing of no weight. Thus in the text, <hi>They have ſpoken words,</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) they let oathes, and covenants paſſe as freely from them
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172134:4"/> yea they make no more of ſolemn covenanting either with God, or man then of letting fall ſo many words, which are but wind. The Lords rule concerning ſwearing is plaine, and full, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſwear the Lord liveth in truth, in Judgement, and in Righteouſnes.</hi> Our oaths muſt be ſquared by the lines of verity, <hi>diſcretion,</hi> and <hi>Charity.</hi> He that ſweares raſhly incurrs guilt as well as he that ſweares a lye or an unjuſt thing, for doth not he alſo take Gods name in vaine? Thence it is that the Lord makes that law concerning him that ſweares raſhly, inconſideratly, <hi>he ſhall be guilty,</hi> and being convinced of ſinne, <hi>he ſhall confeſſe it before the whole congregation, and he ſhall bring his treſpaſſe offering that the Prieſt may make an atonement. Leviticus</hi> 5.4, 5, 6.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when men ſweare faſly in making a Covenant,<note place="margin">When men ſweare falſly.</note> as <hi>Iſrael</hi> here, the Prophet gives in Charge againſt them that they were falſe in the covenant that they made, either with God or their own King, or the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> that had invaded their Land, and made them tributary. Now men are <hi>guilty of this ſeverall waies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Men ſweare falſly, when they ſweare with a falſe heart,<note place="margin">With a falſe heart.</note> having no purpoſe to performe their ingagements either to God or man; when men covenant Reformation, but have no heart to reform, when men covenant righteouſnes, righteous dealing, but intend to be unjuſt ſtill. Thus did <hi>Iſraell</hi> when they made a Covenant with God in <hi>Horeb,</hi> they promiſed God very faire, <hi>All that the Lord ſhall ſpeak we will heare it and doe it,</hi> but the heart ſearching God was well acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their falſhood, therefore ſaith he. <hi>They have well ſaid, all that they have ſpoken. Oh that there were ſuch an heart in them. &amp;c.</hi> Deut. 5.27, 28, 29. Thus did the <hi>Iewes</hi> in <hi>Ioſiahs</hi> dayes, they all covenanted with God for reformation, but they <hi>ſware falſly, Ier.</hi> 5.2. Thus theſe <hi>Iſraelites to the King of Aſſyria,</hi> they embraced all opportunities of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. Thus <hi>Zedekiah</hi> 2, <hi>Chron:</hi> 36.13. Memorable was that of our <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, who ingaged himſelf in a ſolemn oath to the Citizens of <hi>Yorke</hi> to be true to King <hi>Henry,</hi> when he was reſolved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to recover his Kingly dignity,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Men ſweare falſly, when they ſweare with a falſe purpoſe, for a falſe end, with an intention to deceive, making Oaths and Covenants their ſtalking horſe that they may come neere their prey, a meane to fetch over plain hearted men, and a cover for their own wickedneſſe, and weakneſſe. This hath been the courſe of wily Atheiſts, ſeekers
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172134:5"/> of themſelves, and ſlaves to their own baſe luſts, that they might the more eaſily compaſſe their own ends, and make way for the ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their own curſed luſts. Some their luſts of coveteouſneſſe, ſuch were <hi>Hamor</hi> and his Sonne <hi>Shechem,</hi> who uſed this plea to bring the men of their City to embrace the Covenant of circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,<note place="margin">Gen 21, 22 22.23.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall not their Cattell, and their ſubſtance, and every Beaſt of theirs be ours?</hi> Some their luſts of cruelty and unlawfull revenge; thus <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs Sonnes</hi> will contract a ſolemn league with the <hi>Shechemites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Albert</hi> Duke of <hi>Franconia</hi> having ſlaine. the Brother of the Emperour <hi>Lewes</hi> the fourth, and fearing the Emperours diſpleaſure betook himſelf into the ſtrong caſtle of <hi>Bamberg.</hi> The Emperour thirſting after revenge ſought for divers yeares together to take the place, but in vain, at length <hi>Hatto</hi> Arch Biſhop of <hi>Ments</hi> promiſes to deliver <hi>Albert</hi> into the Emperours hand. Going therfore to ſeek him, &amp; pretending friendſhip, he perſwads him to make his peace, and ſolemnly ſwears that if he would goe with him to the Emperour, he would bring him back in ſafety into his caſtle. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> by this curſed wile going out of his Caſtle is brought into the power of <hi>Lewis,</hi> who cuts off his head, and beſtowes his caſtle and goods upon periured <hi>Hatto.</hi> The Emperour approving periury ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied his luſt of revenge, and the falſe Biſhop, acting it, his luſt of coveteouſnes; But they both went not long unpuniſhed.</note> that they may the better circumvent them, and avenge themſelves on them, for the wrong that was done to their Siſter <hi>Dinah. Gen.</hi> 32.13, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Some their luſts of Ambition, <hi>Zedekiah</hi> King of <hi>Judah</hi> being in feare of the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> who were Maſters of the feild, and fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the City, makes a <hi>Covenant with all the people which were at Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, to proclaim liberty unto them.</hi> He brings the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> to <hi>covenant</hi> no more to oppreſſe their Brethren, no more to make them ſlaves. At preſent all act accordingly, they let their <hi>Hebrew Servants goe free,</hi> but upon the removall of the <hi>Caldeans</hi> they cauſed them <hi>to return,</hi> and <hi>brought them into ſubiection againe.</hi> What was the deſigne? Beloved, <hi>Zedekiah</hi> and his Princes being in danger ſeeke to ſecure themſelves, to ſit laſt in their ſeats, by increaſing a party, for this end liberty (a moſt taking thing with an oppreſſed people) is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly purpoſed. That this was the maine deſigne is evident; for no ſooner is the danger removed, but the Covenant is forgotten and laid aſide as out of date. Jt was the brand of <hi>Philip</hi> Father of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, that he deſpiſed an oath, and never made conſcience of any League or Covenant, yet he made often uſe of them, for the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on of his owne Ambitious Ends, in the fetching over of ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple people,</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:172134:5"/>
            <p>Some their luſts of pride and envy. Thus <hi>Saul</hi> adjures the people under a <hi>curſe not to eate any thing untill the Evening;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 14 24.</note> his pretence is zeale againſt the enemies, that the purſuit of them may not be hindred, but his deſigne was to take the glory of the day to himſelf, being grieved at the heart that any ſhould act gloriouſly when himſelfe had plaid the Coward. Curſed hypocrite! in this he hindred much of that dayes glory. Some of uncleanneſſe, yea what villany almoſt can reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on up, which Atheiſticall wretches have not made uſe of an oath to bring about?</p>
            <p>Neither is it any marveile that this hath been ſo common among wicked men, it being the moſt ready way to deceive. The Apoſtle tell us that an <hi>oath for confirmation is to men an end of al ſtrife. Heb.</hi> 6.16. He that wil not take his word, may be taken by his Neighbours oath. It was the uſuall ſaying of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Tyrant. <hi>Sicut pueritalis, itae juramentis homines decipiendi;</hi> Children muſt be fetcht over with cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls, and men with oaths. And this was the conſtant practiſe of <hi>Lewes</hi> the eleventh of <hi>France,</hi> and therefore he would have his Sonne learne that latin, though, no more. <hi>Qui neſcit diſſimulare, neſcit reguare.</hi> It was a ſaying of one of the French Kings (J remember not at preſent his name) that he got more by his pen, than the Engliſh did by his ſword; his meaning was, he got more by falſe Treaties, than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did by fair Wars. Such as theſe are helliſh Covenanters; The good Lord keep them out of <hi>England,</hi> or diſcover them and bring them to ſhame if there be any ſuch. The Turkes have had a cuſtome in making Leagues, when they intended falſhood, they cauſed the Articles to be written in a forraign language, and theſe, though ſworn to, they made no conſcience of; when they intended Truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they cauſed them to be written in their own tongue, and theſe being ſworn to by the grand Seignour, were held ſacred and inviolable. Jf men will be falſe, let them weare out-landiſh ſtuffes, and not cover themſelves with Engliſh cloath.</p>
            <p>It is a peece of the Character of a man fit to inioy communion with God in his Ordinances here: and reſt with God in heaven here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, that he is <hi>one that hath not ſworn deceitfully.</hi> Pſal. 24.4. Deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſwearers are worthy to be caſt out of the Church, and ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly (if they abide ſuch) be kept out of heaven.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Men ſwear falſely,<note place="margin">When they break their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements.</note> when having ſworn they break their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, making no conſcience of performing thoſe things that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172134:6"/> they have covenanted for, and ſworn unto. And this:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Jn a way of <hi>Omiſſion,</hi> according to the variety of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, either to God, or man. When men neglect to doe what they have covenanted for, and ſworn unto, when men let that lye in the duſt, and be laid aſide, or come behind, which they covenanted to advance, and in the firſt place to regard; when men let that live, and connive at that which they have by an oath doomd to death, and ſworne to extirpate. Thus did <hi>Iſrael, they kept not the Covenant of God.</hi> Pſal. 78.10. They Covenanted to embrace all that God ſhould injoyne them, but they refuſed to walke in his law: They Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted to ſerve God with the beſt, and to their utmoſt to advance his worſhip and ſervice, but a ſmall matter muſt ſerve Gods turne, and what they can ſpare muſt content him. <hi>But Curſed be the decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, which hath in his flock a male, and voweth and ſacrificeth unto the Lord a corrupt thing. Mal.</hi> 1.14. They covenanted to lay aſide all Superſtition, all will-Worſhips. But they <hi>Provoked God to anger with their high places,</hi> Pſal. 78.58. This brings to remembrance thoſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages we have concerning <hi>Aſa.</hi> 2 Chron. 15. He and his people <hi>cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted to ſeek God,</hi> that is to ſerve, to worſhip God only, and this in ſtrength of <hi>zeale</hi> and <hi>integrity:</hi> yea they <hi>covenanted to bring</hi> to condign-<hi>puniſhment</hi> any perſon that ſhall act otherwiſe, and that <hi>impartially.</hi> ver. 12, 13. This very <hi>Covenant</hi> at that juncture of time was very <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> for all <hi>Iudah reioyced at the Oath.</hi> But marke (I pray) what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, <hi>Maacoh his mother</hi> is marked indeed for her Idolatry, <hi>depoſed from her reigning,</hi> but not condignly puniſhed according to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. <hi>Yea the high places were not taken away.</hi> ver. 16.17. So ſoon, ſo eaſily can men grow cold in performing that which they have moſt ſolemnly ſworn.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in a way of <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> when men Act contraty to their ingagements, doing that which they have covenanted againſt; when men ſwearing to advance holineſſe, live prophanely covenanting for Truth, countenance Error, when men ſweare to endeavour Union, and nouriſh Diviſion, profeſſe zeale, and act formality, when men co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant righteouſnes, and to give all men their iuſt dues, but live upon ſpoile, and practiſe deceipt and robbery. Thus did <hi>Jſrael</hi> here, they acted contrary to their <hi>Covenant</hi> both with God, and man. Thus did <hi>Achan</hi> in taking of the <hi>accurſed thing,</hi> ſacriligiouſly embezilling that, and impropriating it to his private uſe, which was by ſolemn cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172134:6"/> devoted to the advancement of Gods worſhip and ſervice. See <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7, 11. &amp;c. And was not <hi>Saul</hi> a periur'd perſon who ſweare <hi>that David ſhould not be ſlaine</hi> (1. <hi>Sam</hi> 19, 6.) and yet ceaſed not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to hunt for his life?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Iewes</hi> after their return from captivity, <hi>covenanted to reſpect their poore Brethren and not to opreſſe them,</hi> yea, <hi>they Covenanted againſt ſtrange Wives,</hi> yet acted the contrary, as ye may ſee. <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.10.13.14. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Jt was the great comfort of the godly in very ſad times, that they were true to their ingagements, and ſtood to their covenant. <hi>Al this is come upon us</hi> (ſay they ſpeaking of thoſe ſad times, and ſore troubles they met withal) <hi>yet have we not forgotten thee, neither have we dealt falſly in thy Covenant Pſal.</hi> 44.17. It will be bitterneſſe in the end to him that having ſworne to be true to God, to Man, proves falſe to both. Thus of the firſt thing, the diſcovery of this Sinne. Now of the ſecond.</p>
            <p>How breach of Covenant brings ruine upon a people,<note place="margin">How breach of Covenant brings ruine. It let's in rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating things.</note> or a perſon that are guilty of it. It doth theſe 2. wayes</p>
            <p>Firſt, by letting in ruinating things, opening a wide breach for them to enter in at. The overflowing ſcourge of all ſorts of Plagues followes this Sinne of Periury, of Breach of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It lets in Gods curſe,<note place="margin">Gods curſe.</note> the curſe of that God that is a conſuming fire. This we ſee <hi>Zech.</hi> 5. The Prophet ſees a <hi>flying roll,</hi> the Angell tells him it is <hi>the curſe.</hi> &amp;c. ver. 3. Its entrance is <hi>into the Houſe of the Thiefe,</hi> and <hi>into the houſe of him that ſweareth falſly, it remains there to conſume it, with the Timber thereof, and the ſtones thereof ver.</hi> 4. Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, in the <hi>Lords favour there is life. Jt is God that iuſtifies, who ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne?</hi> If God bleſſe none can curſe; it is not in the power of Devils, or any of their curſed inſtruments to doe any harme, their curſes, their charmes, their inchantments are in vaine. This <hi>Balaam</hi> is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to confeſſe. <hi>How ſhall I curſe, whom God hath not curſed? Or how ſhall I defie, whom the Lord hath not defied? Num.</hi> 23.8. and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he gives councell to them to draw them to breach of Covenant. If God curſe, none can bleſſe; all indeavours to ſave, to repaire the breaches are in vaine, till the ſentence be reverſed. It is a dangerous thing juſtly to procure the curſe of an earthly parent, ſeldome have ſuch curſes prooved vaine;<note place="margin">Gen. 9.25.</note> 
               <hi>Ham</hi> in his poſterity felt the ſmart of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172134:7"/> 
               <hi>Noahs curſe.</hi> Oh then how ſad a thing is it how dangerous to incurre the curſe of the great God. <hi>Curſed be the deceiver</hi> for I <hi>am a great King, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts. Mal.</hi> 1.14.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gods Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>Jt lets in Gods iudgements, and theſe are very waſting, <hi>when the windows from on high are open, the foundations of the earth doe ſhake. The earth is utterly broken down.</hi> When Gods judgements come pouring down upon the earth like a deluge, they carry all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, there is no avoiding of them. <hi>Feare, and the pit, and the ſnare are upon thee O inhabitant of the earth. And it ſhall come to paſſe, that he who flieth from the noiſe of the feare, ſhall fall into the pit, and he that commeth out of the middeſt of the pit, ſhall be taken in the ſnare, See Jſa.</hi> 24.17.18, 19. No ſinne doth more open the Windows of heaven for the letting down a deluge of Iudgments, than this of perjury, of breaking covenant. This lets in ſwift judgement. <hi>J will come neerer to you in iudgement, and J will be a ſwift witneſſe againſt the ſorcerors, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Adulterers, and againſt the falſe ſwearers ſaith the Lord of hoſtes. Mal.</hi> 3:5. <hi>the roll of the Curſe</hi> that enters the Houſe of him that ſweares falſly, and remains there to conſume it, is a flying roll. Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment though ſeemingly club-footed, hath wings to haſten its pace. Though mans judgement ſometimes cannot overtake a faithleſſe perſon,<note place="margin">See Eccleſ. 8.11.12, 13. conferred with ver. 2. <hi>Raro antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentem ſcele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum De ſeruit pede paena claudo.</hi>
               </note> yet Gods iudgement alwayes followes him at the heeles. You ſhal ſeldome find a generation paſt over wherein faithleſſe men have not bin marked, either in own perſons or in their poſterity. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chan</hi> by this ſinne troubles <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and God by his judgements ſoone troubles <hi>Achan. Saul to curry favour with the People breakes the Oath of God,</hi> made with the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> and cauſleſly ſlaies them: But God followes them with his iudgements, and, though we find not himſelfe marked for this ſinne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth of <hi>France</hi> betrayes all that truſt in him, and is himſelf ſo followed by furies before he dyes, that he dares truſt no man. His ſonne <hi>Charles</hi> the eight by perjury, and breach of covenant gets the heire of <hi>Britaine</hi> to wife, but ſoon after in the floure of his years, is ſuddenly cut off, and leaves his crown and bed to be poſſeſſed by his enemy. A certain periured perſon, hearing a Preacher condemne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, and laying open Gods judgements attending it, preſently out of the Atheiſme of his heart ſaid; J doe not ſee the arme with which I forſwore my ſelf ſhorter then the other, but preſently the hand of God overtook him, for that very hand with which he had forſworn, was ſuddenly ſo inflamed, that not being able to indure the torment of it, he was forced to have it cut off. And thus he ſoon ſaw one arme ſhorter than the other.</note> yet his <hi>poſterity</hi> in a ſhort time after ſmart for it 2 <hi>Sam,</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bloudy and deceitfull men ſhall not live one half their dayes, but J will truſt in thee O God.</hi> Pſal. 55.23. This lets in the bittereſt the ſadeſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172134:7"/> judgement. <hi>Judgement ſprings up as Hemlock.</hi> God ſpends the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved Arrowes out of his Quiver of vengeance upon perjur'd perſons.</p>
            <p>God ſends his <hi>evill Arrowet of famine</hi> upon <hi>Jſraell</hi> for <hi>Sauls</hi> breach of covenant, which they at preſent did approve of.<note place="margin">Ezek. 5.16. 2 Sam. 21.1.</note> God threatens to ſend a ſword to avenge the <hi>quarrell of his Covenant.</hi> Warre with its Attendants, plague and famine. Levit. 26.25.26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Who can ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently depaint the ill ſhape of the beaſt-warre? Beloved,<note place="margin">Bellum dicitur quia minime bellum.</note> if there be any iudgement more bitter than other, it is the portion of theſe falſe men. See how the Lord threatens <hi>thoſe ſcornfull men that did rule Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, who thought to ſecure themſelves againſt Gods iudgements, by making lies their refuge, and hiding themſelves under falſhood. The Lord wil bring judgment to the line,</hi> he threatens to follow them with proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, conſtant overflowing and continuall Iudgements, ſo far that it ſhall be <hi>a vexation only to underſtand the report.</hi> And this notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all their defences. See Iſai. 28.14 15.17, 18, 19.20. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is this termed <hi>Gods ſtrange worke.</hi> ver. 21. namely, wonderfull and terrible, ſeeming not to agree with the mildneſſe of a Father to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his children, but rather with the fury of an enemy againſt a ſtranger. The Roman <hi>Cenſors</hi> marked any vice that brought detriment to the common wealth, but none more than periury. The <hi>Egiptians</hi> had a law to behead periur'd perſons as being guilty of a twofold wickedneſſe, <hi>ut qui &amp; pietatem in deos violarent, &amp; fidem inter homines tollerent, maximum vinculum ſocietatis humanae.</hi> When the faithfull faile from among the children of men, and falſe men thinke to ſecure themſelves, and carry all before them, by flattery and fals, hood, <hi>at the ſighing of the needy God will ariſe. Pſal.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>This lets in ſutable iudgement. This ſinne uſually meets with the execution of the Law of Like for Like. <hi>The wicked hath conceived miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and brought forth falſhood.</hi> A bad conception &amp; a worſe birth. But marke what followes. <hi>He made a pit and digged it, and it fallen into the ditch which he made. Pſal.</hi> 7.14, 15. <hi>Zedekiah</hi> and his <hi>Princes,</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> covenant to let their <hi>Hebrew</hi> Servants goe free. They breake this Covenant, and God threatens to proclaim a liberty for them to variety of iudgements, and ſlavery, <hi>J will make you to be removed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the Kingdoms of the earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> See <hi>Jer.</hi> 34.18. Thoſe that againſt covenant oppreſſe their Brethren ſhall fall into the hands of thoſe that ſhall oppreſſe them. Memorable is that ſentence that comes out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172134:8"/> the Aſſyrian. <hi>Jſa.</hi> 33.1. <hi>Wo to thee that ſpoyleſt, and thou were not ſpoyled; and dealeſt treacherouſly, and they dealt not treacherouſly with thee: When thou ſhalt ceaſe to ſpoyle, thou ſhalt be ſpoyled; and when thou ſhalt make an end to deale treacherouſly, they ſhall deale treacherouſly with thee.</hi> The maine ſin provoking this ſentence was <hi>breach of Covenant.</hi> ver. 8. The <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> had by oath contracted a League with <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> &amp; contrary to his covenant invaded his land. This was fully executed. Treacherous <hi>Sennacherib</hi> was ſlain by his treacherous ſonnes as he was worſhipping in the houſe of his God. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.37 And the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> were ſupplanted by the as treacherous <hi>Babilonians.</hi> It was once good ſport to the people of <hi>Athens</hi> (as I remember) that a very Knave was driven into exile by a verier Knave then himſelf. Our <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth by periury recovered his Crown, and his ſons by the cruilty and periury of their falſe Uncle ſoon loſt it. God made the imprecation of the Duke of <hi>Burbon</hi> true by the execution of it, which he falſified in his continued oppreſſion of the <hi>Milanois. The Lord is known by the iudgement which he executeth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rodulph</hi> Duke of <hi>Suenia</hi> by the inſtigation of the Pope and his Miniſters, rebells againſt the Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth. After divers conflicts, at length <hi>Rodulph</hi> is mortally wounded, looſing his right hand: being nigh to death, his right hand being brought unto him, he preſently out of remorſe of conſcience cries out. This is that right hand with which I ſwore featly to the Emperor. <hi>Haec violatae a me fidei argumentum eſt.</hi> In this God ſpeaks plainly that he is an avenger of breach of covenant.</note> 
               <hi>the wicked is ſnared in the work of his own hands.</hi> Pſal. 9.16.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Jt lets in all ſorts of ſin and diſorder, ſin ruines more than wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom reares. <hi>One ſinner,</hi> an eminent ſinner ſwarving from the rules of wiſedom and juſtice, <hi>deſtroyeth much good.</hi> Eccleſ. 9.18. This over throwes <hi>holineſſe</hi> and <hi>honeſty.</hi> See Jer. 5.1, 2. It lets in Atheiſme, and prophanneſſe, and impiety, and all ſorts of oppreſſion. When men are treacherous, and lyars, there is no ſafe living among them, no truſting of them, it is beſt for a man to get <hi>a lodge in the wilderneſſe, to leave ſuch a people and goe from them.</hi> See Ier. 9.2, 3, 4, 5, 6. This ſin is the high way to a ſeared conſcience, it is followed uſually with the plague of the heart, the greateſt plague that can befall any people, any perſon, being commonly Gods concluding ſtroke. This ſin makes men wiſe to doe evill,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theodorick</hi> had a Courtier (a Deacon ſay ſome) that was in favour with him, (upon hope of preferment) became an <hi>Arrian, Theodorick</hi> therefore ſlew him with his own hands (or as others, cauſed him ſoon to be beheaded) ſaying, that he would never be true to his King, that was falſe to his God.</note> and overthrowes all order among men. Jt was the ſaying of <hi>Theodorick</hi> King of <hi>Jtaly.</hi> That he which kept not his faith with God, could never be faithfull to a mortall man.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:172134:8"/>
            <p>And it is the ſaying of the Holy Ghoſt, that <hi>he that loves not his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whom he hath ſeen, cannot love God whom he hath not ſeen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn 4.10.</note> They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not keep faith with God, that care not to keep faith with men.</p>
            <p>Thus of the firſt way, wherein Breach of Covenant lets in Ruine, now of the ſecond.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By making a breach upon preſerving things;<note place="margin">It makes a breach preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving things.</note> This overthrowes the Defences of a People or Perſon, and makes naked.</p>
            <p>This drives God away, who is the <hi>hope of Jſraell,</hi> and <hi>the Saviour thereof in time of trouble. Ier:</hi> 14:8. God profeſſes <hi>he will be with Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell no more,</hi> unleſſe they remove this ſinne of breach of covenant. See <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.12. If God be with us, who ſhall be againſt us? But if God be gone all is gone. <hi>Except the Lord keep the City, the Watchman waketh but in vaine. Pſ.</hi> 127.1. Gods <hi>favour</hi> is the beſt cover,<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.12. Pſal. 32.10.</note> Gods <hi>mercy</hi> is the beſt circumvallation. Jf Gods <hi>heart</hi> cannot be towards a people or perſon nothing can ſecure them. See <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.1. This ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs and infatuates councels, the Nerves of State, and preſervatives of a flouriſhing condition. <hi>Jn the multitude of Councellours there is ſafty,</hi> ſaith the wiſe man. <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.14. <hi>Rehoboam</hi> (the fooliſh Sonne of a wiſe Father) follows this dictate, he conſults with many Counſellors, he conſults <hi>with the old men</hi> that ſtood before <hi>Solomon</hi> his Father, he conſults <hi>with the young men</hi> that were grown up with him, and which ſtood before him, but all to further a rent, while being wilfull he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke the councell of the old men, and embraced the councell of the young, thereby adding fuell to that fire of diſcontent which was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready kindled in the hearts of the people. 1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 12. Will you know the reaſon of this? <hi>The cauſe was from the Lord, that he might perform his ſaying, which the Lord ſpake by Ahiiah the Shilonite, unto Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam the Sonne of Nebat Ver.</hi> 15. This ſaying was, that <hi>God would rent the Kingdom out of the hand of Solomon</hi> (of his ſon) <hi>and give ten Tribes to Jeroboam.</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11.31. The cauſe of this follows, becauſe <hi>Solomon</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too <hi>uxorious</hi>) tollerated Idolatry in his wives, which was a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt breach of <hi>Jſrael's</hi> covenant with their God ver, 33. The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Senators when they firſt entred the Senate-houſe ingaged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a ſolemn oath (according to their then ſacred rights) to lay aſide ſelf, and all by and private reſpects, and in all their conſultations to attend and intend the publique good. While they made conſcience of this &amp; acted accordingly; they, and with them, the common wealth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172134:9"/> were in ſafty and flouriſhed; but when giving way to luſts and paſſions they broke this their oath, they were firſt weakened with civil wars, and ſhortly after became ſlaves to the luſts of cruell Tyrants. When a people are outwardly formall in their ingagements to heaven, and inwardly falſe, God will proceed to doe a merveilous work amongſt them: For the <hi>wiſedom of their wiſe men ſhall periſh, and the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their prudent men ſhall be hid.</hi> Iſa. 29, 13, 14.</p>
            <p>This ruines force: God is the Lord of Hoſts, he commands them, he inables them, God can ſave by miracle, but God will ordinarily ſave by meanes. Ioſhua muſt <hi>chuſe out men, and go out, and fight with Amaleck,</hi> while <hi>Moſes</hi> is praying and acting faith on God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.9. But breach of Covenant will ruine Armies, be they never ſo ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefull, and valourous, and make the Militia of a Nation nothing worth. <hi>Jſrael hath ſinned</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>and they have alſo tranſgreſſed my Covenant. Therefore the children of Jſrael could not ſtand before their enemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>The Roman Armies while <hi>Fides Legionum, and Fides Exercituum</hi> was currant coine, and the Publique Faith both in councells &amp; camps was as good at any private mans bond, carried al before them &amp; made almoſt al the nations of the then known world to ſtoop unto their yoke, but when afterwards they betrayed their truſt, &amp; contrary to the military oath took too much upon them, praeſcribing their Maſters &amp; commanders, raiſing &amp; depoſing whom they pleaſed, looſening the golden reins of diſcipline, &amp; inuring themſelves to maſterfull licentiouſneſſe, they became by degrees the ſpoyle of almoſt all barbarous Nations.</p>
                  <p>This inſolency and perfidiouſneſſe of the Janizaries, hath cauſed the Turkiſh Moon to be at the full, if not in the wane, every day threatning the ruine of that mighty Empire. The <hi>Hungarians</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a fatall overthrow at the battell of <hi>Varna,</hi> in reward of their periury whereunto they were perſwaded by <hi>Iulian</hi> the Popes Legate.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>but turned their backs before their enemies, becauſe they were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.</hi> Ioſh. 7.11, 12.</p>
            <p>This obſtructs Iuſtice and Iudgement the nerves of Policy, and Bulwarkes of a State <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> (Iuſtice) <hi>exalteth a Nation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Iſay 33.5.6.</note> Prov. 14.34. This turnes Iudgement into <hi>hemlock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This makes a breach upon the beſt means of ſafety and deliverance even ſpirituall meanes, faſting and prayer, and hinders them. <hi>Get thee up</hi> (ſaith the Lord to Ioſhua. Ioſ. 7.10, 11.) <hi>wherfore lieſt thou thus upon thy face? Iſrael hath ſinned, and tranſgreſſed my Covenant.</hi> Faſting is to no purpoſe, and prayer will not availe till this ſin of breach of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant be repented of.</p>
            <p>Yea this makes a people or a perſon forfeit all their excellencies. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God, J will even deal with thee as thou haſt done, which haſt diſpiſed the Oath, in breaking the Covenant.</hi> Thou haſt caſt of me, and I will caſt off thee.<note place="margin">Ezek. 16.59.</note> Thou hadſt <hi>avouched</hi> me to <hi>be thy God,</hi> and I
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172134:9"/> had <hi>avouched</hi> thee to be my <hi>peculiar people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 26.17.18.</note> But thou haſt caſt off all feare of me, and I will throw thee out of my favour. Shall man bee looſe, and God be bound? <hi>With the upright man, God will ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upright, and with the froward God will ſhew himſelf froward.</hi> Pſalm. 18.25, 26.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the ſecond thing. How breach of Covenant brings Ruine upon a people or perſon that are guilty of it. Now of the third,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Why breach of Covenant is a ruinating ſinne.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> Becauſe this is a moſt hanious ſinne.<note place="margin">This a ruina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe moſt hainous.</note> Every ſinne hath its weight, the guilt of it enough to cauſe the poor creature to ſink under it; but al ſins are not alike weighty. There are degrees of puniſhment, &amp; therfore degrees of ſinning. The more hanious the ſin, the more dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful the vengeance. God proportionates his meaſure of puniſhing to out manner and meaſure of ſinning. See <hi>Lu.</hi> 12 47, 48. <hi>God will bring iudgement to the line Jſa.</hi> 28.17 Make man's puniſhments aequall with their faults. Now this is a moſt hanious ſinne, a ſinne of the largeſt ſize and weight, for: Firſt, this is a ſinne wherein men doe moſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front Heaven, and riſe up moſt daringly againſt the Divine Majeſty.<note place="margin">A ſin wherein moſt affront heaven.</note>
            </p>
            <p>He that ſweares by Gods name <hi>falſly,</hi> prophanes the <hi>Name</hi> of God. <hi>Lev.</hi> 19:12. God gives it in charge againſt the falſe ſinner, whoſe tongue frames deceipt, that ownes no relations, no ingagements if they croſſe his luſts. <hi>Thou thoughteſt J was altogether ſuch an one as thy ſelf. Pſ.</hi> 50.19:20:21. Periur'd perſons plucke from God his wiſdom, not thinking that all things are preſent before him; or elſe argue him of iniuſtice, as if by connivency he did beare with the malice and faults of the wicked. But God will reprove ſuch. <hi>David</hi> concludes that the wicked hath no feare of God before his eyes, becauſe the words of his mouth are <hi>iniquity</hi> and <hi>deceit,</hi> Pſal. 36.1, 3. <hi>If one man ſin againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Judge ſhall iudge him; but if a man ſin againſt the Lord, who ſhall intreat for him?</hi> 1 Sam. 2.25. God will avenge the wrong that one man does to another, and ſhall he not avenge himſelf on thoſe that manifeſtly riſe up againſt his own greatneſſe and glory? Secondly, This is a ſin wherein men appear moſt falſe among men. It was the agravation of <hi>Zedekiahs</hi> rebellion,<note place="margin">A ſin wherein men appeare moſt falſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men.</note> that he <hi>rebelled</hi> againſt <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar,</hi> who had made him <hi>ſwear by God.</hi> 2 Chron. 36.13. Men love the Treaſon but hate the Traitor. The Punicks faith was a by-word among the Romans. The <hi>Perſians</hi> impoſed everlaſting ſilence on him that was thrice convicted of lying, and made him uncapable of any
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172134:10"/> office,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Selymus</hi> the ſecond cauſed <hi>Keretzen</hi> that betrayed <hi>Giula,</hi> to be rolled to death in an Hogſhead full of ſharp nailes, with this inſcription. Here receive the reward of thy treachery, &amp;c. If thou wert not true to <hi>Maximilian</hi> thy Lord, neither wilt thou be to me.</note> or honor. Scarce any nation ſo barbarous, that have not look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on periured perſons as the vileſt among the children of men.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Becauſe moſt unreaſonable unexcuſable.</note>2. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> Becauſe this is a moſt unreaſonable, a moſt unexcuſable ſin. Our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſhewes the danger of the Iewiſh nation to be very great, becauſe by reaſon of his comming, and ſpeaking to them, they had no <hi>cloak</hi> for their <hi>ſin,</hi> no excuſe for their unbeliefe. <hi>John</hi> 15.22. The more light men ſin againſt, the more inexcuſable are they in their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. In this men ſin againſt the <hi>Law</hi> of God, his expreſſe word, and againſt the <hi>Light</hi> of nature. It is a ſad thing to conſider how eaſily men gull themſelves in a thing of ſo great concernment, with what poor patches they ſeek to cover this their wickedneſſe. Some not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to deny their breach of faith pretend force, they covenanted out of feare, or by reaſon of feare, dare not ſtand to their covenant. Miſerable men, ſlaviſh ſpirits, that feare a man that ſhall dye, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the Lord their maker; that out of the feare of a mortall man, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly lay aſide the feare of the everliving God?<note place="margin">Iſay 51.12.13.</note> Might not <hi>Shimei</hi> have pleaded this? But <hi>Salomon</hi> was wiſe in executing deſerved Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice upon that perjur'd wretch. See 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.42.43. Some pretend fraud, they were overreached, drawn to covenant that which they were not well informed in. Jt is a ſhame that men ſhould be ſo ſilly; but this will no way iuſtifie perjury, when things ingaged for are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, yea indifferent. <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and the <hi>Elders</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> are by a <hi>wile,</hi> brought to enter a <hi>League</hi> with the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> to ſweare to let them live. Afterwards this fraud is detected, the Congregations of <hi>Jſrael</hi> deſire their death, yea murmur againſt the Princes, becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to ſpare them, the people petition their death, but the Princes dare not but let them live, and their reaſon is ſtrong, <hi>Leſt</hi> (ſay they) <hi>Wrath be upon us, becauſe of the Oath which we ſweare unto them.</hi> Ioſh. 9.18, 19.20. <hi>Saul</hi> almoſt foure hundred yeares after breakes this <hi>Oath,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> and his poſterity ſmart for it. Some pretend prae-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, or croſſe ingagements. This no queſtion might in part have been pleaded by <hi>Salomon,</hi> but was no way ſufficient to iuſtifie his breach of Covenant with God, or to ſence off deſerved wrath. <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> loved many ſtrange women, he cleave unto theſe in love. It is probable he contracted with them to allow liberty of conſcience, it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172134:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> is evident that out of his uxoriouſneſſe he connived at, and tolerated their Idolatry. In this he broke Gods convenant, and made a breach upon his own houſe. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.1, 2. &amp;c. Shall we in paying our vowes to men, infringe our vowes to God? Or to keep faith with men break faith with God?</p>
            <p>It is a ſad thing to conſider how men withdraw their oaths, or chip and pare them that they may ſuit with their luſts. Some will ſtraine a little, in it they ſhall pleaſure a friend. Men appearing for themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſide naturall affection. Men appearing for God, plead natures, relations, to croſſe divine ingagements. And is this aequall? <hi>Pericles</hi> requeſted by a friend to do an unlawfull act, replyed, <hi>Oportet me com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modare amitis, ſed uſque ad aras.</hi> Shall not this heathen riſe up in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt many of us? <hi>He that loveth father or mother more than me,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>is not worthy of me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.37.</note> Some pretend conſcience of their ingagements, but ſay it is not yet ſeaſonable as the Iewes. Hag. 1.2. <hi>This people ſay, the time is not come, the time that the Lords houſe ſhould be built.</hi> But marke what followes. <hi>Is it time for you, O ye, to dwell in your cieled houſes, and this houſe lie waſt?</hi> Muſt we firſt attend our profits,<note place="margin">Verſe 4.</note> our pleaſures, our liberties, our priviledges, and then Gods honour?</p>
            <p>I ſpeak nothing of thoſe wretches that covenant to curry favour, or to cover themſelves, or to ſurpriſe others, their own hearts condemn them. <hi>Peter</hi> makes <hi>Ananias</hi> ſee himſelf left without excuſe in his <hi>ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> his breaking his vow. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, 4. A pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern for all thoſe to take heed by, that pretending to advance Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Gods worſhip and ſervice, only ſeek themſelves, their owne honour and glory. The Lord will have open infringers of his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant die without mercy, as being without all excuſe. See <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.2, 3, 4, 5. It was the iudgement of an heathen, that Faith given,<note place="margin">Numa.</note> either in reſpect of the publique, or the private, ſhould be held, and kept, being the honeſt bond of humane ſociety, and the foundation of all right and aequity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> Becauſe this is a leading ſin, a maſter, a mother ſin.<note place="margin">Becauſe a lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinne.</note> The more leading ſins are, the more do they ſpeed, and increaſe ruin. God will have leading ſinners puniſhed, and that without <hi>partiallity,</hi> be they never ſo ſeemingly eminent, be they never ſo neare, ſo deare to us, yea though they be many in number. See <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. throughout the whole chapter. <hi>Ieroboams</hi> ſin was a moſt ruining ſin becauſe a leading ſinne, and this is the brand that is upon record upon him, <hi>Iereboam the ſon of Nebat which cauſed Iſrael to ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:172134:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Now, this is a moſt leading ſin, for, Firſt it hath a ſtrong influence on others. <hi>The heart</hi> (in its naturall eſtate) <hi>is deceitfull above all things.</hi> Jer. 17.9, and therfore prove to be infected by deceit. Mens hearts naturally are prepared tinder on which the ſparks of falſhood alight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting doe moſt readily take.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mak Duffe</hi> fleeing the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of <hi>Mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> came into <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Malcolme Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> and fought to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing right heire to the Crown of <hi>Scotland</hi> to ſeek to recover his right, and therein to free his country from a tyrant. <hi>Malcolme</hi> ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting deceit, pretends in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency by reaſon of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid vices reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in him, as firſt immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate luſt and lechery. To this <hi>Mak-Duffe</hi> replyes, that though this were an horrid vice, yet he would take a courſe to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it. Secondly <hi>Malcholme</hi> tels him that he was the moſt avaratious creature on the earth. To this <hi>Mak-Duffe</hi> replies, that though this were a worſe vice than the other, yet if he would take the crown upon him, there were riches enough in <hi>Scotland</hi> to ſatisfie this greedy deſire. But when laſtly, <hi>Melcholme</hi> tels him that he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to disſimulation, and breach of faith, ſo that he reioyced in nothing ſo much as in betraying thoſe that ſhould truſt him, <hi>Mak duffe</hi> replies, this yet is the worſt of all, and there I leave thee; and ſo bemoaning his own, and his countries miſery break out into teares.</note> One perjured perſon is fit to make many ſuch. It is an eaſie matter for a ſon to imitate a falſe Father, faithleſſe <hi>Cain</hi> hath a faithleſſe poſterity. <hi>Aetas parentum peior avis, Tulit nos nequiores.</hi> God alone can ſet bounds to this prevailing wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, and in exerciſing his free grace this way appears moſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as well as moſt mercifull. The aire is infected where ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> breath at liberty. The <hi>Indians</hi> infected the <hi>Spaniards</hi> with the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>diſeaſe, and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> infected the <hi>Indians</hi> with their unfaithfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Secondly, it hath a ſtrong influence upon the party that is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it. This is a moſt infatuating, a moſt intoxicating ſin. He ſticks at nothing that can eaſily ſwallow periury. <hi>Mak-Duffe</hi> when <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colme</hi> diſſembles with him can find a remedy for other vices, as cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, whoredom, but none for this of perjury, hee lookes upon ſuch a one as deſperate, as paſt all cure. He that lives in this ſin without repentance, hath Atheiſme lording it in his heart, and cannot but more or leſſe have impiety, and diſhoneſty appearing in his life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. See how lively the Lord laies open the vileneſſe of ſuch perſons. Iſay 59.3. &amp;c. <hi>Your lips have ſpoken lyes, your tongue hath mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered perverſeneſſe. None calleth for iuſtice, nor any pleadeth for truth; they truſt in vanitie, and ſpeak lyes.</hi> Here is the Character of theſe men, their fruits follow. <hi>They conceive miſchief, and bring forth iniquity. They hatch Cockatrice eggs, and weave the Spiders web, &amp;c.</hi> ver. 4, 5.6. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>They brood and bring forth al manner of miſchief, horrid, hurtfull, poyſonous, &amp;c. They are ſtrangers to all good, all honeſty, all righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, &amp;c. and therfore no marvell though theſe times were ſo dark and diſmall. We may well apply that to theſe men which the Lord ſpeakes. Deut. 32.32. <hi>Their vine is of the vine of Sodom, and of the fields of Gomorah: their grapes are grapes of gall, their cluſters are bitter.</hi> Their nature is very wicked, their works are worſe.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:172134:11"/>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> Becauſe this is a ſinne that God will by no meanes paſſe by, or leave unpuniſhed. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.7. <hi>The Lord will not hold him guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that taketh his name in vaine.</hi> This awakens vengeance in the Lord, and that eaſily, <hi>One Achan</hi> by his periury troubles all <hi>Jſraell,</hi> God that is truth, and a God of truth, and cannot but ſoone reſent, and readily puniſh falſhood.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the explication and confirmation of this truth, the Uſes briefly follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Let us make inquiry after this. <hi>Have we not ſpoken words ſwearing falſly in making a Covenant?</hi> Is not this the troubler of our <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell?</hi> Is not this the worme that lies gnawing at the root of that gourd that hath heretofore overſhadowed <hi>England?</hi> We are a tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous Nation, the foundations of the earth tremble, all things are out of courſe, we looked for <hi>peace</hi> and behold <hi>trouble.</hi> And is there not a cauſe? can that building long ſtand, the foundations whereof are dayly undermined? <hi>Get thee up Joſhua</hi> (ſaith the Lord) leave off wondering, <hi>Iſraell hath ſinned and tranſgreſſed my covenant.</hi> This was then hidden, is <hi>England's</hi> ſo? I would it might not be ſaid, that <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland's</hi> breach of Covenant is written in ſuch capitall letters that he that runnes may reade it. <hi>Jeremie</hi> in charity hopes the falſhood and rebellion of the <hi>Jewes</hi> had paſſed no further then the <hi>common People;</hi> but he finds to his griefe that the <hi>great men</hi> alſo, who had <hi>more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> or pretended to more knowledge <hi>had altogether broken the yoake, and burſt the bonds Ier:</hi> 5.4, 5. J have nothing here to doe to ſpeak of that horrid raſh common, cuſtomary ſwearing which, though the law of the Land markes, yet paſſeth unmarked in moſt parts of the Land; I ſpeake only to our more ſolemne ingagements and the breach of them. Have we not ſworn with falſe hearts? Are there none that have made lies their refuge, and hid themſelves under falſhood? have we bin true in performing our ingagements to God, to man? have we in the zeale of God according to our Covenant in our ſeverall places, and callings laboured to advance what we have ſworn to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, and to ruine what wee have ſworn to ruine? I ſigh to ſpeak it; how ſoone is that which God hath upon record in heaven almoſt forgotten by us? we ingaged our ſelves for Union, and behold Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Whatſoever is contrary to ſound Doctrine hath gotten dayly ſtrength even ſince we covenanted its extirpation. Never more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſſe and whatſoever is contrary to the power of godlyneſſe, and never leſſe means among us here in the country to curb it. The time
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172134:12"/> permit to ſpeake of particulars. <hi>Men declare their ſinne as Sodom, they hide it not.</hi> Our firſt love is grown cold, we can ſee truth ly trodden under foote, darkneſſe praeferred before light, the blood of precious ſoules drawn forth, and our hearts bleed not for it. Many of us are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſometimes to heare curſing and ſwearing and blaſphemy under our roofes, and out of feare we ſay nothing to it. Where are the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Covenanters? wher are the reformed ones? wher are they that out of conſcience of their ingagements endeavour to their utmoſt to give God, and man their due? Have not all ſorts corrupted themſelves? where is almoſt the free Family? where is the free Congregation? have not private perſons, have not publick ſworn falſly? Are there no falſe Miniſters amongſt us? have theſe done their duty? have theſe <hi>ſtood in the gap</hi> now in theſe times wherein God hath <hi>ſought for a man?</hi> Are there no falſe Magiſtrates? there were ſuch in <hi>Ezra's</hi> dayes, in <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah's</hi> dayes, <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> that with the firſt ſubſcribed the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> and were ſoone <hi>Leaders</hi> in the breach of it. See <hi>Ezra</hi> 10. A Covenant made, broken <hi>Nehe:</hi> 6:17, 18, 19. ſo, <hi>Nehe:</hi> 9.38. and 10. A Covenant made and ſubſcribed by the <hi>Princes, Prieſts,</hi> &amp;c. ſoone after broken as we ſee chap. 13. J would there were none ſuch in <hi>England.</hi> Beloved the ſinne is manifeſt, and hath not God cloſely fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with his vengeance? hath not iudgement broke in ſwiftly, ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſutably? Is there not made a breach upon all our excellencies? doth not our nakedneſſe appeare to our ſhame? <hi>The whole head is [ſick<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the whole heart faint. From the ſole of the foot, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto the head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Allus to Iohn 8.7.</note> 
               <hi>there is no ſoundneſſe, but wounds, and bruiſes, and putirfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſores; Iſa:</hi> 1.5, 6. We are ready all to ſay bring forth the Troubler, let him be ſtoned to death, but who ſhall throw the firſt Stone at him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Let us juſtifie the Lord in al his proceedings hitherto, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire his patience. <hi>The Lord is righteous in all his wayes, and holy in all his workes, Pſ.</hi> 145.17. Proud <hi>Pharoah</hi> whoſe heart was hardened, is forced by the divers iudgements of God, and his differencing in them,<note place="margin">Exod. 9.27.</note> to confeſſe that <hi>God is righteous, but himſelf and his people wicked.</hi> And ſhall we be more hard hearted than he? Beloved, we have had unnatural ſhowers of blood, unſeaſonable ſhowers of raine; the Lord hath ſeemed to threaten us in theſe parts to withdraw the appointed weekes in Harveſt, and to deprive us of the ſeed time: we have had ſtrange diſeaſes, and the hand of God is upon many of our Cattell: Our poore in ſome parts have bin ready to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172134:12"/> periſh for want of bread, and our ſelves want either hand or hearts to relieve them. Strangers have been ready to devoure our ſtore, and we lie under many burthens. <hi>We roare al like Beares,</hi> we murmur, yea in our impatiency we raile; but, beloved, we forget our duty,<note place="margin">Iſa. 59.11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Jt is of the Lords mercies we are not utterly conſumed, his compaſſions faile not. Lam:</hi> 3.22. Have wee bin true to our God? have we been faithfull in our dealings one with an other? have we bin carefull, according to our ſolemn ingagement to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our ſelves, our families, to advance truth, to further peace? My Son, my ſoule, give glory to the Lord God,<note place="margin">Hoſea 14 1.</note> for thou haſt <hi>fallen</hi> by thine <hi>own ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. Why will ye dye</hi> O houſe of Iſraell? <hi>For</hi> I <hi>have no pleaſure in the death of him that dyeth, ſaith the Lord God. Ezek:</hi> 18.31, 32. But <hi>ſhall he eſcape that doth ſuch things? or ſhall he breake the Covenant and be delivered? Ezek.</hi> 17.15. <hi>God hath not dealt with us after our ſinnes: nor rewarded us after our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities. Pſal.</hi> 103 10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Let us labour to ruine this Ruiner, let us repent of this great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and caſt away from us this <hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> whereby we have <hi>tranſgreſſed</hi> againſt the Lord. That ye may be moved hereunto, conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The folly of this thing. Falſnes this way cannot be hid from God, <hi>All things are naked and open unto the eyes of him with whom we have to doe. Heb:</hi> 4.13. <hi>Achan</hi> is ſolitary in his acting periury, in regard of man, but the eye of God is upon him. The falſnes of our hearts cannot be hid from him who is the ſearcher of the heart, and trieth the reines, <hi>Can any hide himſelf in ſecret places, that</hi> I <hi>ſhall not ſee him, ſaith the Lord? doe not</hi> I <hi>fill Heaven and Earth ſaith the Lord?</hi> Ier. 32.24. Shall wee doe well to commit that in the preſence of the All-ſeeing and immortall God,<note place="margin">Ioſh. 7.18 20.</note> which we are aſhamed to own in the preſence of a mortall man? Falſneſſe this way ſhall not be long hid from men, the <hi>Lot</hi> of God ſhall light upon thee, and the alreaching hand of God ſhall ſo overtake thee that thou thy ſelf ſhalt be thine owne betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>God will reprove thee,</hi> The Devill and thine own luſts ſhall be let looſe to diſcover thee. <hi>The Lord ſhall lead thee forth with the VVorkers of iniquity. Pſal.</hi> 125.5. <hi>Evill men and Seducers ſhall waxe worſe and worſe, deceiving and being deceived.</hi> 2 Tim. 3.13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The baſeneſſe of it. It is that which the very light of nature is aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, yee ſhall hardly find any ſo baſe as willingly to own it. The baſeſt language you can give to any is to give him the lie; this is enough amongſt men to iuſtifie a duell, to deſerve a ſtab: Now this is the baſeſt manner of Lying. A Thiefe ſteales ſometimes out of neceſſity, and we will have him hangd, but falſe men live, and the greater Theeves lead the leſſer to the gallowes. This makes unfit for any ſociety, any relation, any imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172134:13"/> It was the glory of our Anceſtors that in their enterprizes they were plain and faithfull, being willing rather to be deceived, than to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: Jt will be our ſhame if we be found contrary minded, The time hath bin when among ſtrangers in the way of comerce and trade, an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh man's word hath been as good as another man's bond, but who will truſt us, if, proving falſe to God, we betray one another. I bluſh to think, if we goe on in breach of Covenant, what a by-word we ſhall be among all neighbour nations, having propoſed our ſelves as a leading pattern to them to enter into the ſame, or like aſſociation or Covenant. This will blemiſh all other excellencies, what is it to be learned, wiſe, valiant, if falſe. The Duke of <hi>Burbou's</hi> credit being crackt by breach of faith, could never by any of his other excellencies be repaired.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The danger of it. But of this at large already, only know, that this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (as ſome other vices) in the guilt of it runs on in a blood: if grace prevent not, it ruines families be they never ſo numerous, never ſo high and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, I might give many inſtances. <hi>Pro.</hi> 14.11.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The good of the contrary. Truth and faithfulneſſe commends to the good of truth. This commends to all men, even our very enemies, and even falſe men have ſomewhat within them bearing witneſſe to men of truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Saul</hi> that makes no conſcience of an oath himſelf, yet will have <hi>David ſweare</hi> he dares truſt him. See 1 Sam. 24.13. This will fence thy heart, and keep thy conſcience unwounded, The faithfull ſhall find the counſelling, comforting,<note place="margin">See Iſay 26.2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 59.15.</note> protecting, delivering preſence of a faithful God, and although in this wicked world, when <hi>truth faileth, he that refraineth from this evill of falſhood maketh himſelf a prey,</hi> yet, <hi>Marke the perfect man, and behold the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, for the end of that man is peace.</hi> Pſal. 37.37.</p>
            <q>
               <p n="1">1. Now that we may remove this great and dangerous evill.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Let us remember our ingagements, and let thoſe vowes of thine that are upon record in heaven, be deeply riveted into thine own heart.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let us be humbled for our by-paſt failings Mourn over thy ſelf, ſmite upon thy thigh, accuſe thy ſelf this day, Mourn over the falſneſſe of thy heart, and ſickneſſe of thy heart, the feebleneſſe of thy heart, that through feare or flattery hath been brought to deale falſly in the Covenant of thy God. Mourn over others, who by their falſhood indanger all.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Let us ſtand faſt to the Covenant, reſolve to pay our vowes, arme our ſelves with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution this way, caſting up our accounts before hand. In a faithfull courſe in all loſſes we ſhall be gainers, In an unfaithfull, our greateſt gaines will be our greateſt loſſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Let us pray to God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. for our ſelves. For pardoning mercy in regard of former failings, for purging mercy for the preſent. <hi>Create in me a clean heart O God, and renew a right ſpirit within me.</hi> Pſal. 51. For preventing and aſſiſting grace for the future, <hi>Keep thy ſervant from preſumptuous ſins, let them not have dominion over me.</hi> Pſal. 19.15. 2. For Magiſtrates thoſe that ſit at the ſtearne, that they being faithfull may promote faithfulneſſe, and take ſome ſpeedy courſe that this ruining ſin may be ſolemnly repented of. And laſtly, for all, that God would heale our backſliding out of his free love.</p>
            </q>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
